Guide to the Papers of the American Irish Citizens Committee for the Re-Election of Mayor William O’Dwyer AIA.002
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
American Irish Citizens Committee for the Re-Election of Mayor William O'Dwyer Papers
1949-1950
AIA.002
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
1.25 linear feet (2 boxes)
The American Irish Citizens Committee for the Re-Election of Mayor William O’Dwyer was formed in 1949 and grew out of a previous entity, the Mayo Men’s Committee for the Election of O’Dwyer, Joseph and Impelletteri. O’Dwyer (1890-1964), a native of Bohola, County Mayo, Ireland had been elected Mayor of New York in 1945. His re-election ticket included City Council President Vincent R. Impellitteri and Comptroller Lazarus Joseph.
Hayden Cudahy, Dorothy, 1922-2010
Provenance
Gift of Dorothy Hayden Cudahy in 1996. This collection was part of an accession of materials from Dorothy Hayden Cudahy, who was secretary of the committee and therefore kept the most complete records of its activities.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The American Irish Citizens Committee for the Re-Election of Mayor William O’Dwyer was formed in 1949 to help re-elect O’Dwyer to a second term as Mayor of New York City. It grew out of a previous entity, the Mayo Men’s Committee for the Election of O’Dwyer, Joseph and Impelletteri. Included on O’Dwyer’s ticket were City Council President Vincent R. Impellitteri and Comptroller Lazarus Joseph. With their headquarters based in the Hotel Commodore, 42nd Street and Lexington Avenue, the committee worked to raise funds, generate publicity, and successfully turn out the Irish vote for the three candidates.
Officers of the committee were
Martin Killeen, Chairman
John Kerry O’Donnell, Treasurer
James FitzPatrick, Financial Secretary
Dorothy Hayden Cudahy, Secretary; and
Hon. Francis T. Murphy, Chairman, Executive Board.
O’Dwyer was re-elected in November 1949 and served until August 1950, when he accepted the position of U.S. Ambassador to Mexico.
William O’Dwyer (1890–1964), a native of Bohola, County Mayo in Ireland, emigrated to New York City in 1910. Prior to becoming Mayor his career in the city included stints as policeman, lawyer, district attorney and decorated war veteran. His papers are at the New York City Department of Records and Information Services, Municipal Archives.
Sources:
McNickle, Chris. To Be Mayor of New York. NY: Columbia University Press, 1993.
O'Dwyer, William (with Paul O'Dwyer). Beyond the Golden Door. Jamaica, NY: St. Johns University Press, 1987.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of reports and minutes, correspondence, financial records, press releases, newspaper ads, radio scripts and printed material generated by the committee from registration week to Election Day, 1949. Of particular interest is the pamphlet This Is O'Dwyer, produced by the committee. Also included in this collection is a newspaper advertisement for the election of William O'Dwyer from his first mayoral campaign in 1945.
Arrangement
The material is arranged alphabetically. An oversize box of advertisements follows the subject files.
American Irish Citizens Committee for the Re-Election of Mayor William O'Dwyer.; American Irish Labor Leaders for O'Dwyer.; FitzPatrick, James.; Impellitteri, Vincent R. (Vincent Richard), 1900-1987; Joseph, Lazarus, 1891-1966.; Killeen, Martin.; Murphy, Francis T.; O'Donnell, John Kerry.; O'Dwyer, William, 1890-1964.; Advertisements.; Financial records.; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Political activities.; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government.; Minutes.; New York (N.Y.); Press releases.; Printed material.
- Inventory
  - American Irish Labor Leaders for O'Dwyer, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Committee Members, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Financial records: Account Book, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Financial records: Bills Paid, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Financial records: Chase Manhattan Bank, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Financial records: Contributions and Expenses, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Advertisements, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8A)
  - Press Releases, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Printed material, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Radio Publicity, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Reports and Minutes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Speakers Committee, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Testimonial Luncheon in Honor of Mayor William O'Dwyer, Mar 1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - This is O'Dwyer pamphlet, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Volunteers (names on cards), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Advertisement - "American Irish Brooklyn Committee for the Election of William O'Dwyer," The Irish Echo, Oct 6, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Advertisements - The Irish Echo, The Irish World and American Industrial Liberator, Nov 5, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)